William Rollin Shipman Papers MS086
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
William Rollin Shipman Papers
1860 -- 1975
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Shipman, William Rollin
MS086
0.5 Linear Feet 1 box
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of Shipman's letters to his parents from 1860-75 covering his family, sermons, and garden.
Biographical / Historical
William Rollin Shipman (1836-1908), a Universalist minister, served as dean of the School of Liberal Arts for seven years (1900-1907).
Born May 4, 1836, in Granville, Vermont, Shipman studied at the local academy and taught in district schools before graduating from Middlebury College with distinction in 1859. He also received his M.A. from his alma mater in 1862 and a D. D. from Saint Lawrence University. Shipman served as the principal of Green Mountain Institute in South Woodstock, Vermont. Prior to leaving Vermont, Shipman had been an avid supporter of the establishment of Goddard Seminary. He continued to serve as the president of the seminary's board of trustees and chairman of its executive committee, while teaching at Tufts. In 1865, Shipman was ordained in the Universalist faith. Although he occasionally preached, he never pastored his own church. He married Martha F. Willis in July 1868 and they had two sons.
Shipman joined the Tufts College faculty in 1864 as Professor of Rhetoric, Logic, and English Literature and also taught other subjects including metaphysics. He was a truly beloved teacher and advisor to his many students, who once even paid for him to take along tour of Europe. Shipman was secretary of the Tufts faculty from 1869 to 1873, and dean of the School of Liberal Arts from 1900 until his retirement in 1907, at which time Shipman was made professor emeritus. He had been a charter member of Tufts' Delta Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa. Shipman died January 15, 1908.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Shipman, William R.; Faculty papers
- William Rollin Shipman, papers, 1860 -- 1975; MS086.001; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of Shipman's letters to his parents from 1860-75 covering his family, sermons, and garden.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Letters, 1860; MS086.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1866; MS086.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1867; MS086.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1869; MS086.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Letters, March-May, 1870; MS086.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Letters, June-December, 1870; MS086.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Letters, February-May, 1871; MS086.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Letters, August-December, 1871; MS086.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Letters, January-May, 1872; MS086.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Letters, June-December, 1872; MS086.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Letters, January-April, 1873; MS086.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Letters, May-December, 1873; MS086.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1874; MS086.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Letters, 1875; MS086.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Letters, undated and fragments, 1860 -- 1975; MS086.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
    This folder has letters that either have no year or are fragments of letters.